You are an ADVERSARIAL fact-checker. Your job is not to agree with this document. Your job is to try to FALSIFY each claim.

The document was produced by an AI deep-research model. It made many web searches but cited only 20 unique domains: aiadvisoryboards.wordpress.com, americanstaffing.net, apa.org, brennancenter.org, cambridge.org, channelnewsasia.com, edelman.com, ipsos.com, kpmg.com, mbs.edu, microsoft.com, news.gallup.com, ourworldindata.org, pewresearch.org, reutersinstitute.politics.ox.ac.uk, slideshare.net, srinstitute.utoronto.ca, thehill.com, unleash.ai, worldvaluessurvey.org.
Treat trade associations, industry bodies, and content farms as promotional sources, not scholarship. Assume this document repeats widely-circulated myths, because that is what such sources recycle.

ABSOLUTE REQUIREMENT: for every claim you MUST actually fetch a web page and paste a VERBATIM QUOTE from it. Do not answer from memory. A confident answer from memory is worthless here: common myths saturate training data, so you would simply repeat them. If you cannot fetch a source, answer 'unsupported' rather than guessing.
Prefer sources independent of the ones listed above. Primary sources, academic and museum pages are best.

Also flag any place where the document contradicts ITSELF.

Return one JSON array. Each element: {"id": "<claim id>", "verdict": "confirmed|false|disputed|unsupported", "url": "<url you fetched>", "quote": "<verbatim quote>", "why": "<one sentence>"}

CLAIMS (66):
  c223577bd: Prioritise recent peer-reviewed academic research from roughly 2023 to 2026, and large longitudinal survey programmes that measure the same question over many years, so that change over time can actually be established.
  c480b3963: So distinguish carefully between (a) a pre-existing long-term trend that continues, (b) a genuine acceleration or reversal that coincides with the arrival of generative AI in late 2022, and (c) a demonstrated causal effect established by experimental or quasi-experimental work.
  cb7afd7ed: The “AI era,” marked notably by the late-2022 debut of powerful generative AI (e.g.
  c73416a97: We prioritize recent academic research (2023–2026) and longitudinal surveys (e.g.
  cb3c212ca: For example, in the United States, the General Social Survey found the share of adults saying “most people can be trusted” fell from 46% in 1972 to 34% in 2018, and a 2023–24 Pew survey found the figure remained at 34% .
  cae739c7c: This suggests a decades-long decline in social trust (especially from the 1970s to 1990s), with levels plateauing at historically low levels in recent years.
  ce859f86d: Globally, an Ipsos poll (Feb–Mar 2022, 22,534 adults in 30 countries) found that on average only 30% of adults agreed that “most people can be trusted.” However, interpersonal trust varies widely by country, from around 56% in China and India to under 15% in Brazil, Malaysia, and Turkey .
  c38a717e0: Denmark ~74%, Norway ~72%) while many low-income or politically unstable countries report very low trust .
  c0fd11955: A global study led by the University of Melbourne and KPMG (surveying 48,000 people across 47 countries in late 2024) found that while 66% of people use AI regularly, only 46% are willing to trust AI systems .
  cf90bed93: Moreover, comparisons to earlier data show a decline in trust coinciding with the rise of generative AI in 2022: in the 17 countries surveyed before ChatGPT’s release, the share of people willing to trust AI fell from about 63% in 2022 to 56% in 2023 , accompanied by a jump in concern about AI’s risks (the proportion “worried about AI” rose from ~49% to 62% over that period) .
  cd21f57b8: The KPMG-Melbourne survey revealed a “clear split” between emerging and advanced economies: roughly three in five people (60%) in emerging economies say they trust AI, compared to only two in five (40%) in advanced economies .
  c05dbbf41: For instance, a May 2023 Bentley University–Gallup survey of 5,458 U.S.
  c0c3d0d61: 68% say AI performs as well as or better than humans at personalizing online content), they are much more skeptical about AI in high-stakes domains – roughly two-thirds of Americans say AI is worse than humans at deciding whom to hire, driving cars, or providing medical advice .
  ca460f179: In short, trust in AI systems themselves does not appear to be rising with AI’s popularity – if anything, global trust in AI has declined since late 2022 (category b), and public confidence in AI’s use remains much lower for sensitive tasks, especially among publics in advanced economies.
  c8cc15ebe: The Reuters Institute Digital News Report 2023 – based on a massive survey of 93,000 online news consumers across 46 countries – found that only 40% of people on average said they trust “most news, most of the time,” down 2 percentage points from the previous year .
  cb529c804: This modest decline in 2022–23 effectively reversed the temporary rise in media trust seen during the COVID-19 pandemic, resuming a prior decades-long slide .
  cf4e5e1e1: media trust spiked in 2020 at the pandemic’s outset, then fell again.) In the United States, trust in mainstream media is near historic lows: as of a late 2024 Gallup poll (Sept 2024, ~1,500 U.S.
  cb2af2468: adults), only 31% of Americans have a “great deal or fair amount” of confidence in the mass media, essentially tied with the record low of 32% first recorded in 2016 .
  c794a64e7: By contrast, in the early 1970s roughly 70% of Americans trusted the media – illustrating a precipitous long-run decline.
  ccb18d9f3: Notably, for the third year in a row, more Americans say they have no trust at all in the media (36%) than say they have at least a fair amount of trust (31%) .
  c1b85cce0: The recent 2-point dip in global news trust from 2022–23 is consistent with pre-existing trends (category a) rather than a sudden acceleration due solely to AI.
  c05e52528: Surveys show the public is highly aware and worried: in an August 2023 YouGov poll of Americans, 85% said they were “very” or “somewhat” concerned about the spread of misleading “deepfake” videos and audio .
  cf911459f: A 2024 study in American Political Science Review simulated scenarios of politicians invoking “fake news” or “deepfake” claims to dodge scandals – a prime example of the liar’s dividend tactic – and found that these false claims helped politicians shore up support among their base, but did not significantly reduce overall trust in media .
  c7de8151f: The OECD’s 2023 cross-national Trust Survey (nearly 60,000 people in 30 countries) reports that on average just 39% of citizens had “high or moderate” trust in their national government in 2023, down slightly from 43% in 2021 .
  c8378c88c: In the U.S., for instance, public trust in the federal government to “do the right thing” most of the time fell from ~73% in 1958 to around 20% in recent years .
  c822174a5: By June 2023, only 16% of Americans said they trust the government in Washington almost always or most of the time, one of the lowest levels in seven decades of surveys .
  c43498088: A 2025 study analyzing thousands of surveys since 1958 concluded that “globally, trust in representative institutions has generally been declining in recent decades” .
  c13776435: Key upcoming events, like the 2024–2026 election cycles in various countries, have fueled speculation that AI-generated fake news or bogus videos could accelerate the erosion of trust in leaders and democratic processes (potentially a category b scenario if it occurs).
  c39e328b4: The 2023 Edelman “Trust at Work” report found a “stunning” 23-point higher trust in “My Employer” compared to societal institutions overall among employees (23-point above the general trust index) .
  c122cec3e: Microsoft’s 2022 Work Trend Index (20,000 people in 11 countries) highlighted “productivity paranoia,” with 85% of business leaders saying the shift to hybrid work made it challenging to trust that employees are productive .
  cf619cf7f: workers (51%) reported in 2023 that their employers were using monitoring technology .
  c760dd214: Research by the American Psychological Association found that monitored employees were significantly more likely to feel micromanaged (56% vs 33%) and to report negative mental health impacts from work .
  cdfe88a41: adults (Dec 2022), 71% opposed the idea of AI making final hiring decisions (only 7% favored it) , and majorities also opposed AI’s use in firing employees or monitoring workers’ performance .
  c7f01220d: job seekers (49%) believe AI recruiting tools are more likely to be biased than human recruiters, according to a 2023 industry poll (American Staffing Association, a promotional source) – a perception that can undermine confidence in AI-based hiring .
  cf6ace724: For example, Pew’s 2022–23 polling found 33% of Americans believed greater use of AI in hiring would reduce bias, but 44% said it would actually make hiring more biased .
  c70b86769: Where a short-term shift has been observed – such as the drop in global AI trust from 2022 to 2023 – it remains challenging to distinguish whether this is an effect of AI’s arrival or part of normal opinion variation.
  c3163a45a: The 2024 APSR experiment found no overall decrease in media trust when subjects were told a real political video was a deepfake , suggesting the liar’s dividend may not be as potent in practice as many fear.
  c04d630af: Our analysis relies on several high-quality sources, including peer-reviewed research and large-scale surveys spanning 2023–2026:
  c6dd8435d: Provided results from a 2025 global survey (48,000 respondents, 47 countries) on public trust, attitudes, and use of AI, conducted by University of Melbourne researchers in collaboration with KPMG .
  c029d5f8e: We cite a 2024 American Political Science Review experimental study on misinformation and the “liar’s dividend,” which is an authoritative scholarly source .
  ce496c2cb: We also reference a 2025 British Journal of Political Science study analyzing global trends in political trust since 1958 – a comprehensive, peer-reviewed analysis covering 143 countries.
  cda0e9767: The Digital News Report 2023 (12th edition) is a well-regarded annual study of global news consumption and trust, based on a 93,000-person survey across 46 countries .
  ccf15e384: For instance, we cited Gallup’s 2024 media confidence poll (approx.
  c9f76f2db: adults) for historical comparisons of media trust , as well as a May 2023 Bentley University–Gallup panel survey (5,458 U.S.
  cf6e00093: interpersonal trust (1972–2018) and a 2023–24 Pew poll on social trust .
  c596995b3: We also used Pew’s Dec 2022 representative survey of 11,004 U.S.
  c5e61ded8: adults on AI in hiring and workplace decisions , as well as a Feb 2023 Pew survey (11,004 U.S.
  cacd3d5ab: We used the CNA piece (2023) mainly to capture the stark 60% vs 40% trust gap between emerging and advanced economies in AI trust .
  c62ab22e2: Provided a summary of the GPO-AI global public opinion survey (21 countries, 2024), offering context on global attitudes toward AI and awareness of ChatGPT .
  cd689a7f1: Microsoft’s 2022 Work Trend Index (survey of 20,000 people across 11 countries) is a large-scale industry study on workplace behavior.
  ce895e9eb: We cited it for the statistic that 85% of business leaders reported lower trust in employee productivity under hybrid work (“productivity paranoia”) .
  c79595195: We referenced an Ipsos Global Advisor survey (22,534 adults in 30 countries, Feb–Mar 2022) on interpersonal trust .
  c0b9c97ba: The APA’s Work and Well-Being Survey 2023 provided insights on employee experiences with workplace monitoring technology .
  cf07edb4e: We included a summary from a 2026 World Values Survey (WVS) analysis covering decades of global data on trust .
  c52df7195: We cited a July 2026 news article reporting results of a Bentley University–Gallup poll (May 2026) on attitudes toward AI’s societal impact .
  c910ce418: The Hill is a reputable political news source; it provided a succinct comparison of 2026 vs 2023 U.S.
  ccfd44d25: University of Melbourne/MBS – Global Trust in AI Survey (2025) – Gillespie, N.
  ccc6466f9: et al., Trust, Attitudes and Use of Artificial Intelligence: A Global Study 2025.
  cc29bc665: Survey of 48,000 respondents in 47 countries (Nov 2024–Jan 2025), conducted by University of Melbourne in collaboration with KPMG.
  c444f4f03: Found 66% of people use AI regularly, but only 46% are willing to trust AI; trust in AI declined from ~63% (2022) to 56% (2023) in tracked countries, with rising concern about AI’s risks .
  c4c1090dd: Notably, ~60% in emerging economies trust AI vs ~40% in advanced economies .
  c6fbf2a04: Pew Research Center – Americans’ Trust in One Another (2025) – Silver, L.
  cb5e39572: social trust: “most people can be trusted” fell from 46% in 1972 to 34% in 2018, with 34% again in a 2023–24 Pew poll .
  c396d915f: Ipsos – Global Interpersonal Trust Survey (2022) – Ipsos Global Advisor poll (22,534 adults, 30 countries, Feb–Mar 2022).
  c2f3187b0: Found average 30% of adults say most people can be trusted, with highest levels in China/India (~56%) and lowest in Brazil/Malaysia/Turkey (<15%) .
  c5282f51f: Reuters Institute Digital News Report (2023) – Newman, N
